原视频名：ULA Stops Selling Atlas Rocket Launches
原作者名：Scott Manley
视频来源：youtu.be/CS8W_4T4Mh0
原视频发布日期：20210827
字幕翻译：旋火
Hello it's Scott Manley here.
你好 我是Scott Manley
This week the United Launch Alliance made a historic announcement signaling the end of an era.
本周 联合发射联盟发布了一个历史性的公告 标志着一个时代的结束
Tory Bruno confirmed that every single Atlas V has now been sold to customers
托里·布鲁诺证实 每一个宇宙神五号现在都已经卖给了客户
and there will be no more.
而且不会再有了
There are 29 launches left
现在还剩下29次发射
and they go to a variety of customers some to NASA, some to the DoD, some to commercial partners.
它们被卖给不同的客户 有些是NASA 有些是美国国防部 有些是商业客户
There's seven of them I believe assigned to Starliners.
我相信其中有7次是分配给星际客机的
Nine of them will be launching project Kuiper for Amazon
9次将为亚马逊发射柯伊伯项目
but after that there is no more.
但在那之后就没有了
By the end of the decade Atlas will no longer be flying
到本年代末 宇宙神将不再飞行
and by the way by the end of the decade the Delta IV will no longer be flying
顺便说一下 到本年代末 德尔塔四号将不再飞行
and Atlas and Delta have been the sort of
而宇宙神和德尔塔一直是那种
they've been at the core of rocket launches in the US going back to the 1950s.
自20世纪50年代起 他们一直是美国火箭发射的核心
Both of these rockets have their roots in ICBM or ballistic missile development.
这两种火箭都源自洲际弹道导弹或弹道导弹的发展
The Thor and the Delta essentially happened in parallel.
雷神和德尔塔基本上是同时产生的
They started building the intracontinental Atlas ICBM, right.
他们开始建造宇宙神洲际弹道导弹 对吧
And they realized that it's complex engine staging system
同时他们意识到 其复杂的发动机分级系统
where two of the engines had to drop off and the third kept running
其中两个发动机必须关闭 第三个发动机则继续运行
was gonna delay things. Make things take a little longer.
这样的飞行时序会延长发射所需时间
So they spun up a program to develop another shorter range rocket called Thor that had a single engine
所以他们启动了一个计划 开发另一种只带有一台发动机的短程火箭 叫做雷神
and instead of having to cross huge continental distances
这样的火箭不需要横跨洲际的距离
they would fly them on planes out to England
而是先用飞机运到英国
and station them there where they could strike Russia.
驻扎在那里 就可以打击俄罗斯了
Now after these things were superseded they got turned into launch vehicles
那么 在这些东西被取代后 它们被变成了运载火箭
so obviously Atlas just evolved over time through various iterations into the Atlas V.
所以很明显 随着时间的推移 宇宙神通过各种迭代演变成了宇宙神五号
The Thor began as the Thor launch system and then they had second stages.
雷神开始是雷神发射系统 然后加上了二级
And eventually one of the second stages was called Delta
最后 其中一个二级被称为德尔塔
so it became the Thor-Delta system and eventually it just became Delta.
所以它变成了雷神-德尔塔系统 最后它变成了德尔塔
So Delta III was the last one that was really closely based on that.
那么德尔塔三是最后一个真正基于此的系统
Delta IV was quite a departure I think.
我认为德尔塔四是一个相当大的变化
The only thing that was really in common between Delta III and Delta 4 was the fairing design
德尔塔三和德尔塔四之间唯一的共同点是整流罩的设计
and one version of the second stage.
以及其中一种二级
But regardless these things are going to stop flying in the next decade
但无论如何 这些东西将在未来十年内停止飞行
and it means that going forward
而这意味着 在未来
almost all the US launch capability will be based on launch vehicles which were not built as ICBMs anymore.
几乎所有美国的发射能力都将基于不再作为洲际弹道导弹建造的运载火箭
These have been built as commercial launch vehicles.
这些都是作为商业运载火箭建造的
Certainly there's a few ICBM derivatives there
当然 那里有一些洲际弹道导弹的衍生品
but this is huge.
但德尔塔和宇宙神代表的是中大型运载火箭
So the reason for this retirement is that the Atlas V uses Russian RD-180 engines
所以退役的原因是 宇宙神五号使用俄罗斯的RD-180发动机
and they use those engines
而且他们使用这些发动机的原因是
because they are arguably the best engines in the world for kerosene and liquid oxygen propellant.
这些发动机可以说是世界上最好的煤油和液氧推进剂的发动机
They get amazing thrust-to-weight ratio.
其有惊人的推重比
They get the best specific impulse.
最好的比冲
They have great throttle control.
节流控制也不错
They're objectively amazing in every way.
客观地说 它们在各方面都很出色
The only thing you might argue is the Merlin engines used on SpaceX's Falcon 9s
你可能争论的唯一一点是SpaceX的猎鹰9号上使用的梅林发动机
have probably better throttle control and they have better thrust-to-weight ratio
可能有更好的节流控制 以及更好的推重比
but really those are only useful if you're landing it.
但实际上 这些只有在你要降落时才有用
Yes I know. Yes.
是的 我知道 是的
But anyway the RD-180s were brought in the 1990s.
但无论如何 RD-180是在1990年代出现的
After the fall of the Soviet Union
在苏联解体后
there were US rocket companies that started looking at potential applications of Soviet technology
有一些美国火箭公司开始关注苏联技术的潜在应用
and they found these engines that were
而他们发现这些发动机是
frankly they didn't believe the numbers when they saw them.
坦率地说 当他们看到这些数字时 并不相信
They thought that there had to be some translation issue.
他们认为 一定有一些翻译问题
No way you can get that kind of performance out of kerosene engine.
你不可能从煤油发动机中获得那样的性能
Well turns out that they had that Russia and the Soviet Union
结果他们发现 俄罗斯和苏维埃联盟
had really put their development expertise
已经真正把火箭发动机开发方面的专长
into developing closed-cycle oxidizer-rich with kerosene engines.
放在了富含氧化剂的闭式循环煤油发动机
And the US hadn't done that.
而美国并没有这样做
The US instead had focused its efforts on hydrogen-based engines
相反 美国将其努力集中在基于液氢的发动机上
从80年代或者氢氧发动机的应用上来说，是的，毕竟能源只打了两次
and the Soviet Union lagged far behind the US in that category.
而苏联在这方面远远落后于美国
But these RD-180 engines were one of the sort of derivatives of this program.
但是这些RD-180发动机是这个计划的衍生品之一
And those have been sold to mount on to Atlas V
而这些已经被卖出去 安装在宇宙神五号上
so it started out actually the first version of an Atlas with the RD-180 engine was the Atlas III.
实际上第一个装有RD-180发动机的宇宙神的版本是宇宙神三
And they launched those six times starting in the year 2000.
从2000年开始 这种火箭发射了六次
And that was just basically an old-school stainless steel Atlas with a slightly different boat tail
那基本上是一个老式的不锈钢宇宙神加上了一个稍微不同的尾部
with the rest of the rocket largely being similar.
火箭的其他部分基本上是相似的
Atlas V was a very heavy redesign on that front
宇宙神五号是在这方面进行了非常大的重新设计
with the one thing that did maintain was the Centaur upper stage
唯一保留的是半人马座上面级
which was largely unchanged at that point.
这在当时基本没有变化
But the Atlas V with those Russian engines has proved to be amazingly reliable.
但是宇宙神五号和那些俄罗斯发动机已经被证明是惊人的可靠
Like it's had basically 100 success rate.
比如 它基本上有100%的成功率
There have been a couple of close misses and not all of those were related to the RD-180
有几次险些失手 但基本都与RD-180无关
2016年3月23日发射的Cygnus CRS OA-6任务
but there was one case for sure where it was launching a Cygnus spacecraft
但有一次可以肯定的是 它在发射天鹅座航天器时
and the main stage cut off five seconds early because of the propellant mixture wasn't set correctly
由于推进剂混合比设置不正确 一级提前5秒关闭了发动机
and thankfully the closed-loop guidance on the second stage Centaur
而幸好二级半人马座上的闭环制导系统
was able to make up the difference and get that payload into orbit
能够弥补差距并将有效载荷送入轨道
only just like the Centaur was supposed to de-orbit itself later with a 10-second burn
这点差距大概只有这点 也就是半人马座本来要进行10秒钟的降轨点火来再入
and only managed a few seconds of that.
但只做到了其中的几秒钟
So that is amazing but the problem has become
那么 这是惊人的 但问题已经变成
that national security launches have started requiring that the RD-180 engines
国家安全发射已开始要求RD-180发动机
no longer be used for national security payloads
不再用于国家安全有效载荷(的发射)
that was initially supposed to happen in a few years ago
这最初应该是在几年前就要实现的
but now the sort of cut-off deadline has been pushed to 2022
但现在的截止日期被推到了2022年
and that means by that date ULA has to have Vulcan flying
而这意味着到那时 ULA必须让火神号飞起来
because they're not going to be selling any more Delta IVs.
因为他们不会再出售任何德尔塔四号
They're not going to be able to sell Atlas Vs.
而宇宙神五又无法出售
They have to have Vulcan flying
火神号必须得飞起来
and Vulcan is their new generation launch vehicle.
而火神号是他们的新一代运载火箭
It's going to do everything that Delta can do,
它得能做到德尔塔能做到的事情
everything that Atlas can do
宇宙神能做到的事情
and it's going to use engines that are built by Blue Origin.
而且它将使用蓝色起源制造的发动机
The BE-4 engines that are using methane and liquid oxygen
也就是BE-4发动机 使用液态甲烷和液氧
and they're going to use closed cycle high performance engines
而这是一台闭循环的高性能发动机
and they have yet to actually deliver the production engines to ULA for integration and testing.
但是他们还没有真正将生产的发动机交付给ULA进行整合和测试
They've been firing this engine on test stand, optimizing them for construction
他们一直在试车台上点火这种发动机 优化它们的结构
so they can build them in the factory.
以便(在定型后)在工厂里制造它们
But that's taking a little longer than they expected
但这比他们预期的时间要长一点
and I'm going to say I've heard that this is a management issue rather than a technological issue
而我想说的是 我听说这更多是一个管理问题 而不是一个技术问题
but anyway regardless that's what's happening there.
但无论如何 这就是那里正在发生的事情
Interestingly because the RD-180 was so critical to US launch capability
有趣的是 因为RD-180对美国的发射能力非常关键
part of the requirements of getting access or being allowed to use the RD-180 on a US launch vehicle
获得或被允许在美国运载火箭上使用RD-180的部分要求是
was that ULA had to get or secure licenses and the necessary technical know-how
ULA必须获得或得到许可证和必要的技术诀窍
to build them themselves to build licensed copies of the RD-180
来制造RD-180的许可副本
and that was an option for a while but ultimately it was never pursued
而这曾是一个选择 但最终没有被采纳
and they decided to go with a completely different rocket design for the future going forwards.
而他们决定采用完全不同的火箭设计来进行未来的发展
So the RD-180 has its roots in the Soviet era Energia rocket.
因此 RD-180起源于苏联时代的能源火箭
That was the massive rocket developed to carry the Soviet Buran Shuttle into orbit
那是为携带苏联暴风雪航天飞机进入轨道而开发的大型火箭
and it would have a hydrogen core
而它会有一个液氢推进剂的芯级
but the boosters on the side were liquid-fueled kerosene liquid oxygen with an RD-170 engine on it
但侧面的助推器使用液体推进剂 也就是液氧煤油 以及RD-170发动机
and those boosters actually they became the Zenith rocket
而这些助推器实际上变成了天顶号火箭
which was later used for by sea launch to put satellites into geostationary orbit from a floating launch platform.
后来被用于海上发射 将卫星从浮动发射平台送入地球静止轨道
So the RD-170 is basically a four nozzle version of the RD-180.
那么RD-170基本上是RD-180的四喷嘴版本
The RD-180 is actually a cut in half version
RD-180实际上是RD-170切成两半的版本
where both of them they have a single set of turbo pumps and plumbing
这两者都只有一套涡轮泵和管道
but they just feed into different numbers of nozzles.
但使用不同数量的喷嘴
Now there's also the RD-191 or the RD-190 and those are single engine versions
那么还有RD-191或RD-190 这些是单发动机 (实际上就是单喷嘴)版本
and they are actually still in use.
而且它们实际上仍在使用
Even after Atlas stops flying the RD-191 will continue
即使在宇宙神停止飞行后 RD-191仍将继续使用
so in the US RD-191 is used in the Antares rocket
那么在美国 RD-191被用于安塔瑞斯火箭中
which is North Grumman's launch vehicle
这是诺斯罗普·格鲁曼的运载火箭
that's used to launch cargo to the space station on the Cygnus spacecraft.
用于发射天鹅座飞船 向国际空间站运输货物
So instead of having a single engine with two nozzles, those are two separate engines.
因此 这些是两台独立的发动机 而不是有两个喷嘴的一台发动机
I think there might have been some licensing requirement that forced them to do this.
我认为可能有一些许可要求 迫使他们这样做(而不是用RD-180)
But also the RD-191 is going to be the main engine used in the Angara rockets
但是 RD-191也将是安加拉火箭使用的主要发动机
and so Angara is the first properly purely Russian-built launch vehicle
那么安加拉火箭是第一个真正的纯俄罗斯制造的运载火箭
because Proton and Soyuz are great Soviet era launch vehicles
因为质子号和联盟号是苏联时代的伟大运载火箭
former Soviet (Union) republics = 前苏联(加盟)共和国，
注意这是一个地理概念，指前苏联地区的国家，而非指苏联本身
but the included parts are built in Russia in Ukraine and probably other parts of the former Soviet republics.
但其中的部件 是在俄罗斯 乌克兰 还可能是其他前苏联共和国地区建造的
And so Russia wanted to have a purely domestic vehicle and that's what Angara is supposed to be.
因此 俄罗斯希望有一个纯粹的国产运载工具 这就是安加拉号的作用
And so that is interesting
因此 这很有趣
because that's actually going to be ultimately replacing the Proton
因为这实际上将最终取代质子运载火箭
and I've sort of talked about this in the past
而我在过去也谈到过这个问题
there are Proton launches still planned but they would really like to retire it
仍然有质子火箭的发射计划 但他们真的想让它退休
其实发射价格并不算很贵，根据en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Proton-M，单次发射价格6500万美元
because it's a very expensive launch vehicle
因为这是一种非常昂贵的运载火箭
and Kazakhstan really doesn't like that amount of really toxic hypergolic propellants in a single rocket.
而哈萨克斯坦真的不喜欢在一枚火箭中大量使用有毒的自燃推进剂
So Angara is going to be the replacement
那么 安加拉将成为替代品
and that means that Protons also going to be retiring in the next decade
而这意味着质子火箭也将在未来十年内退役
so this is a wild decade.
那么这是一个疯狂的十年
We're seeing the end of Atlas, Delta and Proton all these cold war icons disappearing
我们看到宇宙神 德尔塔和质子的终结 所有这些冷战时期的标志正在消失
and being replaced by modern purely civilian launch fields.
并被现代的纯民用发射领域所取代
Okay I mean Proton was never used as an ICBM
好吧 (实际上)质子火箭从未被用作洲际弹道导弹
although it was originally envisaged as an ICBM that could carry a monster warhead.
尽管它最初被设想为可以携带巨型弹头的洲际弹道导弹
It never made it that far thankfully.
幸好它没有走到那一步
And so it shouldn't be surprising given technological progress that these things do have a shelf life.
因此 考虑到技术进步 这些东西有保质期也就不足为奇了
It is amazing that they are still with us after over 60 years
令人惊讶的是 它们在60多年后仍然与我们在一起
but now realize that their time is limited
但现在意识到 他们的时间是有限的
and if you want to see them you should probably start planning now.
而如果你想看到它们 你也许应该现在就开始计划
On the other hand I won't be surprised
另一方面 对这件事 我也不会感到惊讶
if the Soyuz derived from the R-7 keeps flying up to its 100th anniversary.
那就是如果从R-7衍生出来的联盟号一直飞到它的100周年时
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
我是Scott Manley 切记 注意飞行安全
[Music]
[音乐]